Finding Aid for University Council (University of Michigan) records, 1931-1948
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Council (University of Michigan) records 1931-1948
University of Michigan. University Council.
2 linear ft.
87338 Bimu B31a 2
The University Council was originally created to replace the Senate Council in 1931. Membership consisted of the President of the University, members selected by the President, and representatives elected by the different schools and colleges of the University. The Council was concerned with academic policies affecting the University as a whole, or policy questions which concerned two or more schools or colleges. In 1948 The Council was disbanded and most of its functions were taken over by a reconstituted and much more powerful Senate Advisory Committee on Academic Affairs (SACUA). The record group consists of minutes of meetings, 1931-1947 (3 v.); accompanying documents, 1931-1945 (13 v.); committee reports, scattered correspondence, topical files, and material on reconstituted University Council, 1970-1987.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor: 234, 5662, 3572
The collection is open to research.
In May 1931, the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan authorized the Senate of the University to create a University Council. As established, the University Council was to exercise the functions of the Senate Council which it replaced, and the legislative functions of the Senate itself. The Senate, however, retained the right of review over the legislative actions of the Council.
Membership on the Council consisted of the President of the University, members selected by the President, and representatives elected by the different schools and colleges of the University.
The Council was concerned with academic policies affecting the University as a whole, or policy questions which concerned two or more schools or colleges. The Council had five standing committees: 1) program and policy; 2) educational policies; 3) student relations; 4) public relations; and 5) plant and equipment. The committee on program and policy considered matters referred to it by the President or by the other standing committees. It was also charged with the preparation of the program for the meeting of the Council. The other four standing committees had jurisdiction over the various administrative and advisory boards and committees of the University.
In 1948, upon recommendation of the Provost, the Regents approved a resolution which abolished the University Council. Most of its functions were taken over by a reconstituted and much more powerful Senate Advisory Committee on Academic Affairs (SACUA).
The University Council Records include seven series: Standing Committees, Committees (reports), Correspondence and Other Papers, Correspondence with Board of Regents, Topical Files, Minutes (bound volumes), and Accompanying Documents (bound volumes).
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Senate.
- Standing Committees
  The Standing Committees series contains documents relating to amendments and decisions on policies and programs under the jurisdiction of the separate committees.
  - Educational Policies (Box 1)
  - Plant and Equipment (Box 1)
  - Program and Policy (Box 1)
  - Public Relations (Box 1)
  - Student Relations (Box 1)
- Committees (reports)
  The Committees (reports) include progress and informative reports in various areas being monitored by the University Council, such as alumni relations and discipline.
  - Alumni Relations (Box 1)
  - Accredited Schools (Box 1)
  - Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information (Box 1)
  - Calendar (Box 1)
  - Cooperation with Educational Institutions (Box 1)
  - Discipline (Box 1)
  - Extension Service (Box 1)
  - Foreign Students and International Center (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 1)
  - Honors Convocation (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics (Box 1)
  - Latin American Relations (Box 1)
  - Lectures (Box 1)
  - Library (Box 1)
  - Military Science and Tactics (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Orientation Period (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Other Papers
  The Correspondence and Other Papers and Correspondence with Board of Regents series contain letters and several communications involving the University Council.
  - 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1944 (Box 1)
- Correspondence with Board of Regents (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files cover a wide range of materials having to do with the agendas, formation, and management of the University Council itself. One file contains materials relating to Louis A. Hopkins, the University Council Secretary.
  - Hopkins, Louis A. (Box 1)
  - Membership (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Organization (Box 1)
  - Programs and Agenda (Box 1)
  - Questionnaires (Box 1)
  - Three term plan, 1942 (Box 1)
- Minutes (bound volumes)
  The Minutes (bound volumes) of the University Council contain the meeting minutes of the council, and are complimented by the Accompanying Documents (bound volumes) which have narratives and other materials relating to University Council meetings, arranged in chronological order.
  - 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1942 (Box 1)
  - November 9, 1942-May 26, 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 1)